Inventory of the Paramount Pictures Corporation photographs
Hoover Institution Archives
Paramount Pictures Corporation photographs
1942-1943
XX256
Paramount Pictures Corporation.
8 manuscript boxes (3.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Materials used in preparation of motion pictures released in 1944, the first titled Hitler's Gang, depicting the Nazi rise to power in Germany, scenes of party rallies, parades, SS troops, and Adolf Hitler and other Nazi leaders at various stages of their careers; and the second, titled The Story of Dr. Wassell, depicting scenes from southeast Asia during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Historical Note
Hitler's Gang was written by Frances Goodrich and Albert Hackett and directed by John Farrow for Paramount Pictures. Released in 1944, the film stars Robert Watson as Adolf Hitler, and depicts the Nazi rise to power in Germany, with scenes of party rallies, parades, SS troops, and Adolf Hitler and other Nazi leaders at various stages of their careers. As The New York Times noted in a review on May 8, 1944, "There is little point in considering The Hitler Gang as entertainment in the accepted cinema sense. As the most complete pictorial documentation we have to date on the birth and growth of Nazism, it has a place unique, resisting comparison or qualitative judgment. Those of us, and that is practically all-embracing, who would profit by seeing, close up, the genesis and spread of an ideological virus, would do well to see The Hitler Gang."
The Story of Dr. Wassell, directed by Cecil B. DeMille and starring Gary Cooper, Laraine Day, Signe Hasso, and Dennis O'Keefe, was released in 1944 by Paramount Pictures. A Technicolor World War II film set in the Dutch East Indies, the film is based on the wartime activities of U.S. Navy doctor Corydon M. Wassell, which were described by President Roosevelt in a radio broadcast made in April 1942.
Sources: P.P.K., "The Screen: The Hitler Gang, a Picture of Birth and Growth of Nazism, Revealing Activities of Nest of Vipers, at the Globe," The New York Times, May 8, 1944; The Story of Dr. Wassell (1944), Internet Movie Database
Scope and Content of Collection
Collected by the research division of Paramount Pictures, the materials include photographs and a small amount of paper research material used in preparation for two motion pictures released in 1944, the first titled Hitler's Gang, depicting the Nazi rise to power in Germany, including scenes of party rallies, parades, SS troops, and Adolf Hitler and other Nazi leaders at various stages of their careers; and the second, titled The Story of Dr. Wassell, depicting scenes from southeast Asia during World War II.
The reverse of most photographs includes handwritten notes regarding source or the date the copy was acquired by Paramount Pictures. The materials remain in their original order by film title.
Arrangement
The original order and titles of the creator have been maintained.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945--Pictorial works.; Wassell, Corydon McAlmont, 1884--Pictorial works.; Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei--Pictorial works.; National socialism.; World War, 1939-1945--Pictorial works.; Germany--History, 1933-1945--Pictorial works.; Germany--Politics and government, 1933-1945.; Motion pictures
Collection Contents
- Hitler's Gang part I, photographs, volume I
  - Table of contents (Folder 1: 1)
  - Official buildings, pre-Nazi (Folder 1: 2)
  - Official buildings, Nazi (Folder 1: 3)
  - Party offices (Folder 1: 4)
  - Nazi homes, Hitler (Folder 1: 5)
  - Nazi homes, other (Folder 1: 6)
  - Party meetings (Folder 1: 7)
  - Places of entertainment (Folder 1: 8)
  - Army (Folder 1: 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 1: 10)
  - Party before 1933 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Party after 1933 (Folder 1: 12)
- Hitler's Gang part I, photographs, volume II
  - Party rallies, Nuremberg (Folder 1: 13)
  - Armed forces (Folder 1: 14)
  - Official occasions, police (Folder 1: 15)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 1: 16)
  - General (Folder 1: 17)
  - Specific (Folder 1: 18)
  - German, Foreign (Folder 2: 1)
- Hitler's Gang part I, photographs, volume III
  - Automobiles (Folder 2: 2)
  - Trains (Folder 2: 3)
  - Airplanes (Folder 2: 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 2: 5)
  - Nazi (Folder 2: 6)
  - Others (Folder 2: 7)
  - Flags and medals (Folder 2: 8)
  - Youth (Folder 2: 9)
  - Civilians (Folder 2: 10)
- Hitler's Gang part I, photographs, volume IV
  - Hitler (Folder 2: 11)
  - World War (Folder 2: 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 2: 13)
  - Anti-Semitism (Folder 2: 14)
  - Concentration camps (Folder 2: 15)
  - Nazis (Folder 2: 16)
  - Others (Folder 2: 17)
  - No Good (Folder 3: 1)
  - Uniforms (Folder 3: 2)
- Hitler's Gang part II, photographs, volume I
  - Cast index (Folder 3: 3)
  - Max Amann (Folder 3: 4)
  - Walter Darre Burger (Folder 3: 5)
  - Anton Drexler (Folder 3: 6)
  - Kurt Eisner (Folder 3: 7)
  - Mathias Erzberger (Folder 3: 8)
  - Herman Esser (Folder 3: 9)
  - Cardinal Faulhauber (Folder 3: 10)
  - Gottfried Feder (Folder 3: 11)
  - Wilhelm Frick (Folder 3: 12)
  - Captain Godin Gehrlich, Josef Goebbels (Folder 3: 13)
  - Goebbels aide, Frau Goering (Folder 3: 14)
  - Hermann Goering (Folder 3: 15)
  - Karin Goering (Folder 3: 16)
  - Graf Gurtner (Folder 3: 17)
  - General Hammerstein and General Wilhem Von Groener (Folder 3: 18)
  - Frau Hanfstaengel, "Putzi" Hanfstaengel (Folder 3: 19)
  - Reinhold Hanisch (Folder 3: 20)
  - Rudolf Hess (Folder 3: 21)
  - Reinhard Heydrich (Folder 3: 22)
  - Heinrich Himmler (Folder 3: 23)
  - Adolf Hitler (Folder 3: 24)
- Hitler's Gang part II, photographs, volume II
  - Heinrich Hoffmann (Folder 3: 25)
  - Sergeant Hubermeyer, Dr. Alfred Hugenberg (Folder 3: 26)
  - Kriebel (Folder 3: 27)
  - Krupp, Landsberg warden, Robert Ley (Folder 3: 28)
  - General Erich Ludendorff (Folder 4: 1)
  - Lutze (Folder 4: 2)
  - Dr. Otto Meissner (Folder 4: 3)
  - Rudolf Nadolny (Folder 4: 4)
  - Pastor Niemoeller (Folder 4: 5)
  - Poehner (Folder 4: 6)
  - Walter Rathenau (Folder 4: 7)
  - Angela Raubel (Folder 4: 8)
  - "Geli" Raubel (Folder 4: 9)
  - Colonel Reichenau, Ernst Roehm (Folder 4: 10)
  - Alfred Rosenberg (Folder 4: 11)
  - Hjalmar Schachtt (Folder 4: 12)
  - Schaub, Julius Schreck, Dr. Sobottendorf, Dr. Stenglein, Julius Streicher (Folder 4: 13)
  - Frau Strasser, Gregor Strasser (Folder 4: 14)
  - Otto Strasser (Folder 4: 15)
  - Fritz Thyssen (Folder 4: 16)
  - Marinus van der Lubbe (Folder 4: 17)
  - Dietrich von Eckart (Folder 4: 18)
  - Ritter von Epp (Folder 4: 19)
  - Paul von Hindenburg (Folder 4: 20)
  - Gustav von Kahr (Folder 4: 21)
  - General von Lossow (Folder 4: 22)
  - Konstantin von Neurath (Folder 4: 23)
  - Franz von Papen (Folder 4: 24)
  - Joachim von Ribbenthrop (Folder 4: 25)
  - von Schirach, Reichter von Scheubner, General von Schleicher (Folder 4: 26)
  - General von Seekt (Folder 4: 27)
  - von Seisser, Wagner (Folder 4: 28)
  - Weber (Folder 4: 29)
  - Miscellaneous, characters, etc. (Folder 4: 30)
- Hitler's Gang part II, photographs and research materials, volume III
  - Locations (Folder 4: 31)
  - Exterior Western front (Folder 4: 32)
  - Interior section German trench (Folder 4: 33)
  - Interior German regiment headquarters (Folder 4: 34)
  - Exterior woods (Folder 4: 35)
  - Section of battlefield, shell hole (Folder 4: 36)
  - Interior hospital (Folder 4: 37)
  - Interior barracks (Folder 4: 38)
  - Interior hospital, reception, interior hotel, ballroom (Folder 4: 39)
  - Interior meeting hall, exterior street corner, interior army barracks (Folder 4: 40)
  - Exterior barracks courtyard and von Epp's wife, interior von Epp's office (Folder 4: 41)
  - Interior Sternecker's beer house backroom (Folder 4: 42)
  - Interior office, German Worker's Party (Folder 4: 43)
  - Interior beer hall (Folder 4: 44)
  - Exterior woods (Folder 4: 45)
  - Interior Sterneckerbrau beer hall (Folder 4: 46)
  - Interior kitchen Sternecker beer hall, exterior Nazi headquarters (Folder 4: 47)
  - Interior Nazi headquarters (Folder 4: 48)
  - Nazi headquarters, 2nd floor to exterior street, Munich (no photographs) (Folder 4: 49)
  - Interior Jewish store, Munich (Folder 4: 50)
  - Interior church (Folder 4: 51)
  - Interior meeting hall to interior Krone circus (no photographs) (Folder 4: 52)
  - Exterior Ludendorff's villa (Folder 5: 1)
  - Interior Ludendorff's study and exterior field, Munich (Folder 5: 2)
  - Interior Goering's cellar to interior Hitler's office (no photographs) (Folder 5: 3)
  - Interior Burgerbraukeller (Folder 5: 4)
  - Interior artists' room to exterior Munich street barricade (Folder 5: 5)
  - Exterior Munich street, November 9, 1923 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Exterior side street or alley to interior Hitler's room (no photographs) (Folder 5: 7)
  - Interior dining room, Landsberg Fortress, December 1924 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Exterior Landsberg Fortress (Folder 5: 9)
  - Interior Hitler's bedroom study (Schaub's apartment) (Folder 5: 10)
  - Exterior Hitler's cottage, Bavarian mountains (Folder 5: 11)
  - Interior Hitler's living room to interior Munich café (no photographs) (Folder 5: 12)
  - Interior opera house balcony, Munich (Folder 5: 13)
  - Interior music studio to interior dining room, Hitler's cottage (no photographs) (Folder 5: 14)
  - Interior kitchen, Hitler's cottage (Folder 5: 15)
- The Story of Dr. Wassell photographs
  - Bibliography and source list (Folder 5: 16)
  - Unnumbered materials and maps (Folder 5: 17)
  - Numbered photographs
    - 1-25 (Folder 5: 18)
    - 16-50 (Folder 5: 19)
    - 51-75 (Folder 5: 20)
    - 76-100 (Folder 5: 21)
    - 101-125 (Folder 5: 22)
    - 126-150 (Folder 5: 23)
    - 151-175 (Folder 5: 24)
    - 176-200 (Folder 5: 25)
    - 201-225 (Folder 6: 1)
    - 226-250 (Folder 6: 2)
    - 251-275 (Folder 6: 3)
    - 276-300 (Folder 6: 4)
    - 301-325 (Folder 6: 5)
    - 326-350 (Folder 6: 6)
    - 351-375 (Folder 6: 7)
    - 376-400 (Folder 6: 8)
    - 401-425 (Folder 6: 9)
    - 426-450 (Folder 6: 10)
    - 451-475 (Folder 6: 11)
    - 476-500 (Folder 6: 12)
    - 501-525 (Folder 6: 13)
    - 526-550 (Folder 6: 14)
    - 551-575 (Folder 6: 15)
    - 576-600 (Folder 6: 16)
    - 601-625 (Folder 7: 1)
    - 626-650 (Folder 7: 2)
    - 651-675 (Folder 7: 3)
    - 676-700 (Folder 7: 4)
    - 701-725 (Folder 7: 5)
    - 726-750 (Folder 7: 6)
    - 751-775 (Folder 7: 7)
    - 776-800 (Folder 7: 8)
    - 801-825 (Folder 7: 9)
    - 826-850 (Folder 7: 10)
    - 851-875 (Folder 7: 11)
    - 876-900 (Folder 7: 12)
    - 976-1000 (Folder 7: 13)
    - 1001-1025 (Folder 8: 1)
    - 1026-1050 (Folder 8: 2)
    - 1051-1075 (Folder 8: 3)
    - 1076-1100 (Folder 8: 4)
    - 1101-1125 (Folder 8: 5)
    - 1126-1150 (Folder 8: 6)
    - 1151-1175 (Folder 8: 7)
    - 1176-1200 (Folder 8: 8)
    - 1201-1225 (Folder 8: 9)
    - 1226-1250 (Folder 8: 10)
    - 1251-1275 (Folder 8: 11)
    - 1276-1300 (Folder 8: 12)
    - 1301-1325 (Folder 8: 13)
    - 1326-1350 (Folder 8: 14)